<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Michal Parusinski - Personal Site - Linux, packaging, AppImage, Docker</title><link href="https://michal.parusinski.me/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://michal.parusinski.me/feeds/linux-packaging-appimage-docker.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://michal.parusinski.me/</id><updated>2022-09-03T16:00:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>Converting docker containers into AppImages</title><link href="https://michal.parusinski.me/converting-docker-containers-into-appimages.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-09-03T16:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-09-03T16:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Michal Parusinski</name></author><id>tag:michal.parusinski.me,2022-09-03:/converting-docker-containers-into-appimages.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In Linux, software is conventionally distributed through packages, usually compressed folders including
executables, installations scripts and various configuration files. These packaging formats come in various
flavors like deb packages, RPMs, and many others. While very useful, these packaging formats have a downside:
they are distribution specific. Even if two distributions …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In Linux, software is conventionally distributed through packages, usually compressed folders including
executables, installations scripts and various configuration files. These packaging formats come in various
flavors like deb packages, RPMs, and many others. While very useful, these packaging formats have a downside:
they are distribution specific. Even if two distributions use the same packaging format, like say Ubuntu
and Debian, they are not compatible. Meaning that a deb package built for debian is not expected to work on
Ubuntu and vice-versa. In goes even further, packages may not be compatible between two different releases
of the same Linux distribution, for instance Debian stable and Debian unstable. The main consequence
of this limitation is that software needs to be built for every combintations of Linux distribution / releases
out there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For simple open source software this isn't usually a big issue, as volunteers can usually take the code
and release it for the distribution of their choice making small adjustments to the code (at least in
principle). For more complicated software and proprietary software this is trickier. However
there is a solution to this problem: recently new
universal, meaning distribution agnostic, packaging formats have been created. The main ones are Flatpak, Snaps
and AppImage. But there are many others, technically Docker is also a means to distributed software (usually
server-side software) on many Linux distributions (as well as Windows). Steam distributables can also be counted, if you
think about it. And even Nix packages are in some way distribution agnostic as you can install Nix
on many Linux distributions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I personally think AppImage lacks a little bit of love. It does not offer as many features as Flatpak or Snaps, which
handle sandboxing, software distribution, and sharing frameworks, but it is very simple and easy to grasp.
AppImages is already fairly popular amongst QT applications, electron applications, and some games like OpenRA.
By the way that is no coincidence, among the tools to build appimages, some are specifically tailored
for QT applications and electron applications. This, in my view, creates a disparity, so I wondered
if I can make a difference. So I decided to create another tool to create AppImages, but from Docker
containers, a tool I am familiar with. Furthermore the creation of Docker images and containers is very
well documented and the collection of publically available Docker images is very large.
The tool's name &lt;cite&gt;docker2appimage&lt;/cite&gt; available on Github at &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/mparusinski/docker2appimage"&gt;https://github.com/mparusinski/docker2appimage&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have a container called &lt;cite&gt;relaxed_beaver&lt;/cite&gt;, to create an AppImage which triggers the container default
command, you run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;docker2appimage&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;relaxed_beaver
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can perform more complex tasks like request &lt;cite&gt;docker2appimage&lt;/cite&gt; to create a container from the
alpine Docker image and create a container that calls &lt;cite&gt;ls&lt;/cite&gt; and give the AppImage the name &lt;cite&gt;alpine-ls&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;docker2appimage&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-x&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;ls&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;--name&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;alpine-ls&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-i&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;alpine
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to work the tool requires the &lt;cite&gt;appimagetool&lt;/cite&gt; AppImage to be accessible on the path as well
&lt;cite&gt;imagemagick&lt;/cite&gt; to be installed on the system. The entire tool is a simple shell script for it is designed
to be portable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is an even more complex example where we create an universal binary for ripgrep a popular alternative for
grep&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;docker&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;run&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-it&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;--name&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;ripgrep&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;ubuntu&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Creates a container called neofetch&lt;/span&gt;
apt-get&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;update&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;amp;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;apt-get&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;install&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-y&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;ripgrep&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Command within the container&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nb"&gt;exit&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Leave the container&lt;/span&gt;
docker2appimage&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-x&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;rg&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;ripgrep
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last commmand creates an AppImage called neofetch from container neofetch which launches neofetch&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most Docker images are server side software (e.g. nginx), OS containers (e.g. alpine) and programming
frameworks. Naturally &lt;cite&gt;docker2appimage&lt;/cite&gt; will fit well to create CLI only AppImage. This is not what
AppImage are usually intended, they are usually intended for Desktop applications. It is still possible
to create GUI applications, and there is a case for CLI AppImages as a replacement for statically compiled
binaries. In other words this offers an approach for portable CLI applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are some limitations of course. Many Docker images default commands are shells like bash, sh, ...
one might even include Python as a type of shell. AppImage works by doing tricks with environment variables
and Fuse to create a pseudo virtual environment where a command is launched from within the AppImage.
This makes handling shell commands trickier, so it is not supported, instead it is better to use
the &lt;cite&gt;-x&lt;/cite&gt; flag that allows the user to specify the command to launch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project is still ongoing development to support many applications and Linux distributions.
If you have some time and are curious do not hesitate to test the tool and report any bugs you see.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="Linux, packaging, AppImage, Docker"></category></entry></feed>