<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Michal Parusinski - Non classé</title><link href="https://michal.parusinski.me/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://michal.parusinski.me/feeds/non-classe.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://michal.parusinski.me/</id><updated>2018-05-19T17:03:00+02:00</updated><subtitle>Senior Software Engineer</subtitle><entry><title>Made it to the front page of EGC 2018</title><link href="https://michal.parusinski.me/made-it-to-the-front-page-of-egc-2018.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-05-19T17:03:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-05-19T17:03:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Michal Parusinski</name></author><id>tag:michal.parusinski.me,2018-05-19:/made-it-to-the-front-page-of-egc-2018.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image0" src="https://egc2018.it/files/news/images/36335495032-1491322fcf-o.th_870x446.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently I made to the front page of the European Go Congress 2018
(Pisa) web page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://egc2018.it/en/news/view/id-32.html"&gt;EGC's article&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="Non classé"></category></entry><entry><title>What to learn from the Cambridge Analytica story</title><link href="https://michal.parusinski.me/what-to-learn-from-the-cambridge-analytica-story.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-03-30T12:14:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-03-30T12:14:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Michal Parusinski</name></author><id>tag:michal.parusinski.me,2018-03-30:/what-to-learn-from-the-cambridge-analytica-story.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you are using Facebook and intend to keep using it the Cambridge
Analytica
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2018/03/facebooks-cambridge-analytica-scandal-explained/"&gt;story&lt;/a&gt;
can teach a few good practices to protect your privacy. Now of course
nothing will be as safe as not having a Facebook account but there are
sensible steps. Also I won't mention typical security …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you are using Facebook and intend to keep using it the Cambridge
Analytica
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2018/03/facebooks-cambridge-analytica-scandal-explained/"&gt;story&lt;/a&gt;
can teach a few good practices to protect your privacy. Now of course
nothing will be as safe as not having a Facebook account but there are
sensible steps. Also I won't mention typical security and privacy
settings recommendation because there are already many websites treating
this (for instance
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.techradar.com/how-to/internet/facebook-privacy-and-security-tips-1307505"&gt;https://www.techradar.com/how-to/internet/facebook-privacy-and-security-tips-1307505&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Avoid using apps or&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;answering quizzes:&lt;/strong&gt; These may look benign
but some of them are aimed at harvesting data. In the scandal it
appears some apps could access your friend's data as well. At least
Facebook claims the accessing the friend's data part is fixed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keep your number of friends low&lt;/strong&gt;: Facebook clearly wants the
opposite by constantly suggesting friends but friends on Facebook is
precisely what Cambridge Analytical used to access so many accounts.
They only surveyed 250000 accounts but through their friends they got
access to 50 million accounts. In principle Facebook doesn't let
third parties access friends data anymore but having people you don't
know (well) or trust in your Facebook friend list is a risk. So ask
yourself do you really need to have 1000 friends?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Treat Facebook data as public even&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;if you set tight privacy
options&lt;/strong&gt;: There are a couple of reasons for this. Firstly Facebook
isn't in the business of keeping data completely hidden, secure and
private. To survive as a company they need to sell access to some of
that data to clients like advertisers. As a company they have to walk
a fine line between privacy demanded by their users and openness
demanded by their clients. Preventing malicious access to data in
those conditions is especially difficult. Add in the fact that
Facebook developers and admins despite being some of the best in the
world aren't perfect, they operate a complex website and mistakes
happen. Malicious access to Facebook data has happened and will
probably happen again. Secondly Facebook has a popularity curse.
Their website and data is one of the primary target on the whole
internet for hacking. The treasure is just too valuable to many
malicious hackers and not just random individuals but also big
companies and governments. Finally there is the problem of mass
exposure. When you interact on Facebook, you tend to interact with
hundreds or even thousands of people. Facebook is not like a
discussion in your living room but more like a permanent public
rally. Now you can mitigate this to some extent with the privacy
settings but it isn't as simple as it sounds. They're complex and
have serious limitations in practice (see
.&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2010/04/facebook-timeline"&gt;https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2010/04/facebook-timeline&lt;/a&gt;). So even
if Facebook is secure it is hard to guarantee all your Facebook
friends access Facebook securely (many people have malware on their
computer). To summarise it is far harder to restrict access to your
content on your Facebook than you might think, so it might be wise to
treat it as public discourse.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</content><category term="Non classé"></category></entry><entry><title>New blog | Nouveau blog</title><link href="https://michal.parusinski.me/bonjour-tout-le-monde.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-01-06T18:37:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-01-06T18:37:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Michal Parusinski</name></author><id>tag:michal.parusinski.me,2018-01-06:/bonjour-tout-le-monde.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hello, for 2018 I am restarting my blog from scratch. In part because in
the transition from Wordpress to Pelican and because of my own silly
mistakes I lost a lot of content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bonjour, pour 2018 je recommence mon blog à partir de zéro. En partie
parce que durant la …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hello, for 2018 I am restarting my blog from scratch. In part because in
the transition from Wordpress to Pelican and because of my own silly
mistakes I lost a lot of content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bonjour, pour 2018 je recommence mon blog à partir de zéro. En partie
parce que durant la transition de Wordpress à Pelican et à cause de mes
propres stupides erreures j'ai perdu du contenu.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="Non classé"></category></entry></feed>